Aying
아잉
We grew up together since childhood
우리는 어릴 때부터 함께 자랐어요
in my eyes
내 눈에
You are different from all the women in this world
당신은 이 세상 모든 여자와 달라요
You've been treating me since I was little
당신은 내가 어렸을 때부터 나를 치료해 왔어요
Different from everyone in this world
이 세상의 모든 사람과는 다르다
I have long been attracted to you
나는 오랫동안 당신에게 매력을 느꼈습니다
Aying
아잉
You also understand my infatuation, right?
너도 내 열광을 이해하지?
It's time for the young master to take medicine
젊은 스승이 약을 먹을 시간이다
Don't worry
괜찮아요
Taozi will definitely be able to find Captain He
Taozi는 반드시 He 선장을 찾을 수 있을 것입니다.
tomorrow
내일
Still heading to the southeast road
아직 남동쪽 길로 향하고 있어
have a look
보세요
Can you meet Tao Zi?
Tao Zi를 만날 수 있나요?
yes
예
Young Master
젊은 스승
Take medicine first
약을 먼저 드세요
newspaper
신문
General Pei
페이 장군
The remnants of Guo Zhi's troops have gathered reinforcements
Guo Zhi의 남은 군대가 지원군을 모았습니다.
The troops are now at the gates
이제 군대가 문 앞에 와 있다
How is the military strength?
군사력은 어떻습니까?
More than ten thousand
만 이상
Outnumbered and outnumbered
수적으로 열세이고 열세
Can't hold it
참을 수 없어
Abandon the city
도시를 버리세요
This is absolutely impossible
이건 절대 불가능해요
Seventeen Lang told us
세븐틴 랭이 알려줬어요
We need to defend the city well
도시를 잘 방어해야 한다
Now we run away without a fight
이제 우린 싸우지도 않고 도망쳐
this
이것
The enemy's strength is ten times ours
적의 힘은 우리의 10배
hit what
뭘 쳐?
how to spell
어떻게 쓰는지
Send an order
주문 보내기
Abandon the city
도시를 버리세요
The soles of these feet need to be oiled again
이 발바닥에 다시 기름칠을 해야 해
I'd better go quickly
빨리 가는 게 좋을 것 같아
Clean it up
청소해라
Lao Bao
라오바오
Business still needs to be done
사업은 아직 해야 한다
This city will be abandoned
이 도시는 버려질 것이다
Why is this dirty work so tiring?
이 더러운 일이 왜 그렇게 피곤합니까?
I have to do it all
다 해봐야지
Everything is in the back hall
전부 뒷홀에 있어요
We'll find more people to do it separately.
우리는 별도로 그것을 할 수 있는 더 많은 사람들을 찾을 것입니다.
Be more agile
더 민첩하게 행동하세요
Why are you still standing there?
왜 아직도 거기 서 있나요?
Let's go
갑시다
Why go?
왜 가나요?
poison
독
go in
들어가다
what is this
이게 뭔가요
nothing
아무것도 아님
Hurry up, hurry up
서둘러, 서둘러
come here
이리 오세요
you you you
너 너 너
come over
이리와
Let's go
갑시다
OK OK
그래 그래
Don't move here
여기서 움직이지 마세요
Junye
준예
Master Jun, let me try to see if it’s poisonous.
준 사부님, 독이 있는지 한번 보도록 할게요.
Go, go, go
가, 가, 가
Stop
멈추다
Come over come over
이리로 와 이리로 와
I'm coming
나는 간다
What is this?
이게 뭔가요?
OK OK OK
오케이 오케이 오케이
Let's go, let's go
가자, 가자
do not move
이동하지 않습니다
Don't move, don't move, don't move
움직이지 마세요, 움직이지 마세요, 움직이지 마세요
Thanks
감사해요
little lady
작은 아가씨
Where are you going?
어디 가세요?
Are you tired from walking?
걷다 지치셨나요?
We'll give you an idea
우리는 당신에게 아이디어를 줄 것입니다
You raise your little face
당신은 작은 얼굴을 들어
Let's see if he's handsome or not
그 사람이 잘생긴지 아닌지 봅시다
If this is Jun
이게 준이라면
No need to leave today
오늘은 떠나지 않아도 돼
Lady
숙녀
I'm here
나는 여기 있다
This official is sorry
이 관계자는 죄송합니다
Clumsy Jing, she is ignorant
서투른 징, 그녀는 무식하다
Haven't been out much
많이 나가지 않았어
This money will buy you a drink
이 돈으로 술 한잔 사줄게
Magnanimity
관대함
Go, go, go
가, 가, 가
Yes Yes Yes
예 예 예
Have a drink tonight
오늘 밤에 한잔하세요
drink drink drink
마셔 마셔 마셔
Don't think I don't know
내가 모른다고 생각하지 마세요
you follow me
너는 나를 따라와
I just want military rations
난 그냥 군사배급을 원할 뿐이야
That
저것
You are quite self-aware
당신은 자기 인식이 꽤 강한 편이에요
release
풀어 주다
The shopkeeper comes to the upper room
가게 주인이 위층 방으로 온다
okay
좋아요
This store does not provide credit
이 매장에서는 크레딧을 제공하지 않습니다.
You want to stay for two days and get a room, right?
이틀 동안 머물면서 방을 구하고 싶죠?
Get a deposit of fifty yuan first
먼저 보증금 50위안을 받아보세요
Fifty cash deposit
50현금 보증금
Shopkeeper
가게 주인
Can you be accommodating?
수용할 수 있나요?
Let me stay today
오늘은 머물게 해주세요
tomorrow
내일
I will definitely pay you the rent
집세는 꼭 갚아줄게
ok
좋아요
accommodating
친절한
How can I stay in a hotel if I don’t have money?
돈이 없는데 어떻게 호텔에 묵을 수 있나요?
Look at you
당신을 보면
from top to bottom
위에서 아래로
Wearing such a shabby look
이렇게 초라한 표정을 짓고
I
나
get out get out get out
나가라 나가라 나가라
no
아니요
Could you please be accommodating?
좀 부탁드려도 될까요?
Look, I have a bulging belly
봐, 나 배가 불룩해
Go out to the shopkeeper
가게 주인에게 나가서
get out get out
나가다 나가다
I have money here
나 여기 돈 있어
There is a large group of people ahead
앞으로 많은 사람들이 모여있습니다
Coming this way
이쪽으로 온다
Their horses are very good
그들의 말은 아주 좋다
high speed
고속
Then let's retreat quickly
그럼 빨리 퇴각하자
So irritating
너무 짜증나
Guo Zhi, this bastard
궈즈, 이 새끼야
As expected to be in the same group as the bad guy surnamed Sun
예상대로 쑨이라는 악당과 같은 그룹이겠지
Not to mention taking over our cottage
우리 별장을 인수하는 것은 말할 것도 없고
And they chase us like rabbits
그리고 그들은 토끼처럼 우리를 쫓아다닌다
Chased all over the mountain
산 전체로 쫓겨났어요
No
아니요
what you do
당신이 무엇을
It's Mr. Cui
미스터 큐이입니다
It's our Mr. Cui who's here.
여기 와 있는 사람은 우리 Cui 씨입니다.
Cui Gongzi
추이공즈
Who is Mr. Cui?
추이 씨는 누구입니까?
Sounds like a pretty boy
예쁜 소년 같은데
Invite you two
두 분을 초대합니다
What do you two need?
두 분에게 필요한 것은 무엇입니까?
Even if you tell me
말해봐도
Don’t delay if you are small
당신이 작다면 지체하지 마십시오
You two have a rest
너희 둘은 쉬어라
You still act
아직도 연기하는구나
I will believe it if the show continues
방송이 계속되면 믿을게
What for?
무엇 때문에?
I want to take advantage of me when I'm not paying attention
내가 주의를 기울이지 않을 때 나를 이용하고 싶다
One needle will stun me
바늘 하나가 나를 놀라게 할 것이다
do not worry
걱정 하지마
If there is a chance
기회가 있다면
I'm going to stun you with a needle
바늘로 찔러버릴 거야
Young Master
젊은 스승
Have you seen Captain He?
캡틴 히(Captain He)를 보셨나요?
We met at the cottage
우리는 별장에서 만났어요
she is safe
그녀는 안전해요
only
오직
In order to get rid of Guo Zhi's people
곽지의 백성을 제거하기 위해
We divided into two groups
우리는 두 그룹으로 나뉘었어요
That's good
좋아요
Continue to explore the whereabouts of the captain
계속해서 선장의 행방을 탐색하세요
Chen Xing
첸 싱
I'll leave this matter to you
이 문제는 당신에게 맡기겠습니다
yes
예
look
바라보다
I'd just say he's a pretty boy.
나는 단지 그가 예쁜 소년이라고 말하고 싶습니다.
What's wrong, doctor?
무슨 일이에요, 박사님?
I didn't feel the Hua pulse
후아맥박이 느껴지지 않았어요
The fetus in your wife’s belly
아내 뱃속에 있는 태아
I'm afraid I can't keep it
지켜주지 못할까봐
It doesn't matter
그것은 중요하지 않습니다
is not what it means
그게 무슨 뜻인지는 아냐
I mean, adults are important.
즉, 어른이 중요하다는 것입니다.
Madam’s pulse
부인의 맥박
It's the wind evil that causes high fever that won't go away
사라지지 않는 고열을 일으키는 것은 바람의 악이다
Must have been injured
부상을 입었나봐요
lost again
또 길을 잃었다
Fortunately, she has a strong foundation
다행스럽게도 그녀는 탄탄한 기초를 가지고 있습니다.
How can I hold on until now?
지금까지 어떻게 버틸 수 있나요?
yes
예
Previously on the mountain
예전에 산에
Her leg was injured
그녀의 다리가 다쳤어요
That's it
그게 다야
I'll write a recipe
레시피를 쓸게요
You take the medicine according to the prescription first
먼저 처방전에 따라 약을 복용하세요.
Then I'll buy some bruise pills
그럼 내가 멍든 약을 좀 사올게
Grind it with wine
와인으로 갈아서
Apply it to Madam's injured area
마담님 상처난 부위에 발라주세요
will get better soon
곧 좋아질 거야
I'm tired
피곤해요
Give
주다
Let's have some drinks tonight
오늘 밤에 한잔 하자
There's more here
여기에 더 많은 것이 있습니다
Let's have some more
좀 더 먹자
have
가지다
Don't grab, don't grab
잡지 마세요, 잡지 마세요
Our Cui family army has sufficient military rations
우리 추이 가문 군대는 충분한 군사 식량을 보유하고 있습니다
If it's not enough, I'll get it again
부족하면 다시 받을게요
thank you
감사합니다
Give
주다
Fragrant
향기로운
Not bad
나쁘지 않다
Wait a minute
잠깐 기다려요
I will follow our young master
나는 우리 젊은 스승님을 따르겠습니다
Let's go together
같이 가자
fine
괜찮은
Eat
먹다
Then after eating
그럼 식사 후에
Let's set off together
함께 출발하자
Set off
출발하다
Where are we going?
우리는 어디로 가는 걸까요?
Of course he went to our Cui Jiajun
물론 그는 우리 Cui Jiajun에 갔다
Our Cui Jiajun
우리 최자준
Never treat your own people badly
결코 자기 백성을 함부로 대하지 마십시오
Just join our Cui Jiajun
Cui Jiajun에 합류하세요
This kind of thin flour pancake
이런 얇은 밀가루 팬케이크
There is something to eat every day
맨날 먹을게 있는데
that is
그건
What is this
이게 뭔가요
long-eared brothers
귀가 긴 형제
Aren't you going to find the Zhenxi Army?
Zhenxi 군대를 찾지 않겠습니까?
Eat slowly
천천히 먹어
Let's go after eating
밥 먹고 가자
Didn’t that girl say that before?
그 여자가 전에 그런 말을 하지 않았나요?
She is the concubine of the emperor's grandson
그녀는 황제 손자의 첩이다.
Eloped with Shishiro
시시로와 함께 도망쳤다
This peach is her maid
이 복숭아는 그녀의 하녀야
How
어떻게
Taozi becomes a member of the Cui family army again
도자는 다시 추이 가문 군대의 일원이 됩니다
You don’t know this, right?
당신은 이것을 모르죠?
Maybe she is the two of them
어쩌면 그 사람이 그 둘일지도 몰라
She is in Cao Ying, but her heart is in Han
그녀는 Cao Ying에 있지만 그녀의 마음은 Han에 있습니다.
Anyway, Seventeen Lang said
아무튼 세븐틴 랭이 말했지
She is one of her own
그녀는 그녀 자신 중 하나입니다
Then she must be one of our own
그렇다면 그녀는 우리 중 하나임에 틀림없어요
Eat, eat
먹어, 먹어
peach girl
복숭아 소녀
I'll give you this cake
이 케이크를 줄게
We don't want to eat anymore
우리는 더 이상 먹고 싶지 않아요
Yeah
응
Even if I give it to you, I won’t even eat it.
줘도 안 먹어요.
Back to you
당신에게 돌아
We won't eat
우리는 먹지 않을 것이다
Give it all back to her
그녀에게 다 돌려줘
Don’t eat, don’t eat
먹지 마세요, 먹지 마세요
What are you doing?
뭐하세요?
Eat
먹다
Such good pancakes
정말 좋은 팬케이크
Why don't you eat it?
왜 그것을 먹지 않니?
exactly
정확히
Eat whatever you want
먹고 싶은 것은 무엇이든 먹어라
After eating
식사 후
I'll take you to Wangzhou
왕저우로 데려다줄게
Go to Zhenxi Army
진시군으로 이동
Come and eat
와서 먹어
well
잘
Zhenxi Army
진시군
Find the Zhenxi Army
진시군 찾기
eat eat eat
먹다 먹다
How dare you
어떻게 감히
Let me rob you openly
내가 공개적으로 당신을 강탈하자
Don't know what is good or bad
뭐가 좋은지 나쁜지 모르겠어
No
아니요
This cake is really delicious
이 케이크 정말 맛있어요
Why don't you try it?
한번 시도해 보는 게 어때요?
If it weren't for food
음식이 아니었다면
I'll make some medicine for you
내가 약 좀 만들어줄게
I don't care if you live or die
네가 살든 죽든 상관없어
A Niang
아니앙
When you are sick, you still know how to call me mother
아플 때에도 나를 엄마라고 부르는 법을 아시나요?
A Niang A Niang
아니앙 아니앙
Walk
걷다
I must live
나는 살아야 한다
A Niang
아니앙
Walk
걷다
Such a cunning and ruthless woman
이런 교활하고 무자비한 여자
A Niang
아니앙
Even if you are sick, you will only call me mother.
아파도 엄마라고만 불러요.
Take medicine
약을 복용
A Niang
아니앙
I will definitely live
나는 반드시 살 것이다
If it weren't for the military rations,
군용배급만 아니었으면
I'll choke you to death
목이 막혀 죽게 해줄게
What are you doing
뭐하세요
You won’t explain it anyway
어차피 넌 설명 안 할 거야
Where to go for military rations
군배급금 구하러 가는 곳
Being around me is also a burden
내 곁에 있는 것도 부담이 돼
I think
제 생각에는
I might as well kill you with one knife.
칼 하나로 널 죽이는 게 나을지도 몰라.
just kill me
그냥 날 죽여줘
your leg is hurt
다리가 다쳤어
What are you doing here?
여기서 뭐하는거야?
Sorry
죄송합니다
What can't you do to me?
당신은 나에게 무엇을 할 수 없습니까?
In fact, at that time
사실 그 당시에는
After I stun you
내가 당신을 기절시킨 후
I quickly went up from the cellar
나는 급히 지하실에서 올라갔다.
I thought they wouldn't
나는 그들이 그렇지 않을 것이라고 생각했다
Attack my husband and mother-in-law
남편과 시어머니를 공격하다
I thought
나는 생각했다
I will definitely find the time
나는 반드시 시간을 찾을 것이다
save them
그들을 구해줘
I pride myself on being smart and capable
나는 똑똑하고 유능하다고 자랑한다.
but i didn't expect
하지만 난 기대하지 않았어
In the end, we couldn't save them.
결국 우리는 그들을 구하지 못했습니다.
I saw
나는 보았다
You are in front of the grave of the old hunter couple
당신은 늙은 사냥꾼 부부의 무덤 앞에 있습니다.
flowers
꽃들
Also engraved with the word "en"
"en"이라는 글자도 새겨져 있습니다.
I knew you would regret it
후회할 줄 알았어
I have buried them
나는 그것들을 묻었다
I just wish I couldn't save them
난 그냥 그들을 구하지 못했으면 좋겠어
when you are sick
당신이 아플 때
I keep calling Aniang
계속 애니앙한테 전화해
When I was young
내가 어렸을 때
I live in Border Fortress
나는 국경 요새에 산다
one day
어느 날
all the men in the city
이 도시의 모든 남자들
They all left the city to fight
그들은 모두 싸우기 위해 도시를 떠났습니다
did not expect
기대하지 않았다
But there is another enemy
하지만 또 다른 적이 있다
Around the city
도시 근처
At that time, my mother-in-law kept calling me
그때 시어머니가 계속 전화를 하셨다.
let me go from the well
나를 우물에서 나가게 해주세요
Climb out and escape
올라가서 탈출하세요
All the women in the city were left
도시의 여자들은 모두 떠났어
Fight together
함께 싸워라
until the last minute
마지막 순간까지
Wait until dad and I come back
아빠랑 내가 돌아올 때까지 기다려요
Saw my grandma
할머니를 봤어요
See all their bodies
그들의 몸을 모두 보아라
They were all hung on the city wall
그들은 모두 성벽에 걸려 있었다
their blood
그들의 피
Dyeing the city walls red
성벽을 붉게 물들이다
I remember
기억해
Zeng Jingbiao of the imperial court
황실의 Zeng Jingbiao
The general’s wife of Yingzhou
영주의 장군 부인
For Mrs. Wu Lie
우 거짓말 부인을 위해
At that time, Jieshuo attacked the city
그때 Jieshuo가 도시를 공격했습니다.
Mrs. Wu Lie fought hard and refused to retreat.
Wu Lie 부인은 열심히 싸웠고 후퇴를 거부했습니다.
Died for the city
도시를 위해 죽었습니다
so
그래서
your mother
당신의 어머니
She is also a member of the Detachment of Women
그녀는 또한 여성 분리(Detachment of Women)의 회원이기도 합니다.
yes
예
North Korea's Central Banner
북한의 중앙 깃발
only one person
단 한 사람
But at that time
하지만 그 당시에는
The Detachment of Women Defending the City
도시를 지키는 여성들의 분리
A total of one hundred and twenty-nine people
총 129명
each of them
그들 각각
Why is she not the mother-in-law of my children?
왜 그녀는 내 아이들의 시어머니가 아닌가?
Why are they not grandma’s children?
왜 그들은 할머니의 아이들이 아닌가?
But they
그러나 그들은
To save more people
더 많은 사람을 구하기 위해
Go to death resolutely
결단코 죽음을 맞이하라
My father asked me
아버지가 나에게 물으셨다.
Still remember your mother-in-law
아직도 네 시어머니를 기억해
The last thing I said to you?
내가 마지막으로 한 말은요?
Ah Ying heard what her mother said
아잉은 엄마가 하는 말을 들었다
Your father is now
네 아버지는 지금
He must be bringing someone with him
그 사람은 분명 누군가를 데리고 왔을 거야
Go back quickly
빨리 돌아가라
Now go west after leaving the house
이제 집을 나서서 서쪽으로 가세요
I will definitely meet your daddy
난 꼭 네 아빠를 만날 거야
do you know
당신은 알고 있나요
Go quickly
빨리 가세요
A Niang
아니앙
The enemy has already entered
적이 이미 들어왔어
You'll die if you do this
이러면 죽는다
good boy
착한 소년
Defending the city is a mother’s duty
도시를 지키는 것은 어머니의 의무
You are young
당신은 어린
Living is your duty
사는 것이 당신의 의무이다
do you know
당신은 알고 있나요
Mom, I won’t leave
엄마, 나 안 갈게요
I will be with you till death
나는 죽을 때까지 당신과 함께 할 것입니다
good boy
착한 소년
There is hope only when you are alive
살아있을 때만 희망이 있다
I don’t know my mother until I’m alive
나는 살아있을 때까지 어머니를 모른다
Why did he die?
그는 왜 죽었나요?
I do not go
난 가지 않아
live and grow up
살고 자라
Only in the future will you be able to
앞으로도 그럴 수 있을 거에요.
Help more people
더 많은 사람들을 도와주세요
i hope one day
언젠가는 좋겠다
Damn Aying
젠장 아잉
It can also save many people
많은 사람을 구할 수도 있다
Walk
걷다
Go quickly
빨리 가세요
I do not go
난 가지 않아
Walk
걷다
Auntie told me
이모가 나한테 말했어
you must live
당신은 살아야합니다
you only live
넌 오직 살기 만 해
Only then did I know why I died
그제서야 나는 내가 왜 죽었는지 알았습니다
only alive
오직 살아있다
Only then can we see hope
그래야만 희망을 볼 수 있다
I asked my mother-in-law to run away with me
시어머니에게 같이 도망가자고 했어요
Aniang said she couldn't leave
아니앙은 떠날 수 없다고 말했다
If they escape
그들이 탈출하면
Bad guys can seize this frontier fortress
악당들이 이 국경 요새를 점령할 수 있습니다
Many, many people will be killed by then
그때쯤 되면 아주 많은 사람이 죽게 될 것이다.
To save more people
더 많은 사람을 구하기 위해
she can't go
그 사람은 갈 수 없어
This is what you were at the hunting lodge
이것이 당신이 사냥 오두막에 있었던 일입니다.
What's the reason why a needle stung me?
바늘에 찔린 이유는 무엇입니까?
You and I both have a heavy responsibility.
당신과 나 모두 무거운 책임이 있습니다.
we only live
우리만 산다
Only those who are diligent can have hope
부지런한 자만이 희망을 가질 수 있다
Only in this way can we save more people
그래야만 더 많은 사람을 구할 수 있다
Stop drinking
술 좀 그만 마셔
Are you taking medicine?
약을 먹고 있나요?
This Xie Changer
이 Xie 체인저
How dare you compete with this girl?
감히 이 여자와 경쟁할 수 있나요?
Next time I see him
다음에 그를 만나면
I will definitely let him
나는 반드시 그에게 허락할 것이다
Diarrhea for three days and nights
사흘 밤낮 동안 설사를 했다.
Let him know how powerful this girl is
이 여자가 얼마나 강력한지 그에게 알려주세요
long-eared brothers
귀가 긴 형제
Unexpectedly, Shichiro
의외로 시치로
Turns out to be the emperor's grandson
황제의 손자로 밝혀졌습니다.
Why didn't you tell us earlier?
왜 우리에게 미리 말하지 않았나요?
Brother Zhao
자오 형제
Why are you beating yourself?
왜 자신을 때리나요?
I used to be a bitch
나 원래 개년이었거든
The Seventeenth Lang is the grandson of the emperor
17대 랑은 황제의 손자이다.
He is the coach of our Zhenxi Army
그는 우리 Zhenxi 군대의 코치입니다
This is great
이것은 훌륭하다
Second brother
둘째 동생
Didn't we all agree before?
전에는 우리 모두 동의하지 않았나요?
Let's go to Zhenxi Army together
함께 Zhenxi 군대에 가자
By the time
그때쯤에는
Let's follow General Pei
페이 장군을 따라가자
And Shikiro
그리고 시키로
Kill the enemy together and make meritorious deeds
함께 적을 죽이고 공덕을 세우십시오
right
오른쪽
good
좋은
Follow Shikiro
시키로를 따르라
Kill the enemy and make meritorious service
적을 죽이고 공을 세운다
good
좋은
After that
이후
We are in the same army
우리는 같은 군대에 있어요
are brothers
형제예요
right
오른쪽
Come
오다
They are colleagues and brothers
그들은 동료이자 형제다.
Let's go, lady
가자 아가씨
Slow down, I'll help you
천천히 하세요, 제가 도와드릴게요
Chopsticks
젓가락
Don't grab, don't grab
잡지 마세요, 잡지 마세요
Don't grab it
잡지 마세요
Give it to the kids first
아이들에게 먼저 주세요
daughter daughter daughter
딸 딸 딸
store
가게
You say
당신은 말한다
Slower
느리게
What's going on here
무슨 일이야?
The lady doesn’t know something
그 여자는 뭔가를 모른다
this morning
오늘 아침
As soon as the city gate opens
성문이 열리자마자
So many people poured in
정말 많은 사람들이 쏟아져 들어왔어요
Said it was General Guo
궈 장군이라고 하더군요
Captured Wangzhou City
점령된 왕저우 시
The Zhenxi Army suffered a defeat
진희군은 패배했다
Just run away all the way
그냥 끝까지 도망쳐
General Guo sent troops to pursue him all the way.
궈 장군은 그를 끝까지 추격하기 위해 군대를 보냈습니다.
Killed many people
많은 사람을 죽였습니다
He also said that he was a spy of the Zhenxi Army
그는 또한 자신이 Zhenxi 군대의 스파이라고 말했습니다.
Don't let anyone go
누구도 보내지 마세요
Look at these people
이 사람들 좀 보세요
It's a hard time
힘든 시기야
old man
노인
I want to ask
나는 묻고 싶다
where are you from
어디서 오셨나요
what's happening here
여기서 무슨 일이 일어나고 있나요?
With this order from Governor Sun,
쑨 지사님의 이번 명령으로
General Guo went back to Wangzhou
궈 장군은 왕저우로 돌아갔다
Talk about us people
우리 사람들에 대해 이야기해 보세요
What kind of spy is this?
이것은 어떤 종류의 스파이입니까?
Look
바라보다
look at us
우리를 봐
What kind of spy does he look like?
그는 어떤 종류의 스파이처럼 보입니까?
This fight goes back and forth
이 싸움은 왔다 갔다 하네
Suffering
고통
Or common people?
아니면 일반인?
General Guo fought back to Wangzhou
궈 장군은 왕저우(Wangzhou)에 반격했습니다.
What about the Zhenxi Army?
Zhenxi 군대는 어떻습니까?
Where did the Zhenxi Army go?
진희군은 어디로 갔나요?
All were killed
모두 살해당했습니다
Killed until rivers of blood flowed
피의 강이 흘렀을 때까지 살해당했습니다
Said a few escaped
몇몇은 탈출했다고 하더군요
General Guo is looking for spies all over the city
궈 장군은 도시 곳곳에서 스파이를 찾고 있습니다.
Leave quickly
빨리 떠나라
If caught
적발된 경우
as a spy
스파이로서
That would be beheading
참수형이겠죠
Gone, gone
사라졌다, 사라졌다
long-eared brothers
귀가 긴 형제
So what should we do next?
그러면 우리는 무엇을 해야 할까요?
anyway
그래도
We all have to go back to Wangzhou first
우리 모두 먼저 왕저우로 돌아가야 해요
The Zhenxi Army sounds pretty powerful
Zhenxi Army는 꽤 강력한 것 같습니다.
Why did we lose the battle?
우리는 왜 전투에서 패했는가?
Although the Zhenxi Army is powerful
진시군은 강력하지만
But General Guo has many soldiers.
하지만 궈 장군에게는 군인이 많습니다.
Standing behind General Guo
궈 장군 뒤에 서다
But Governor Sun
하지만 쑨 주지사는
I heard people say
사람들이 말하는 걸 들었어요
What is this Governor Sun?
이 Sun 주지사는 무엇입니까?
The reincarnation of the evil star in the sky
하늘의 사악한 별의 환생
Not only did the emperor and his family
황제와 그의 가족뿐만 아니라
Killed them all
다 죽였어
He also slaughtered several cities
그는 또한 여러 도시를 학살했습니다.
This time we enter Wangzhou.
이번에는 왕저우(Wangzhou)에 들어갑니다.
Killed many more people
더 많은 사람을 죽였어
What kind of spy is the Zhenxi Army?
진시군은 어떤 스파이인가?
They are clearly our poor people.
그들은 분명히 우리의 가난한 사람들입니다.
what are your plans
당신의 계획은 무엇입니까
What are your plans?
당신의 계획은 무엇입니까?
You follow my food
넌 내 음식을 따라와
But now we people
하지만 이제 우리 사람들은
Already in Bingzhou
이미 Bingzhou에 있습니다.
The Zhenxi Army retreated from Wangzhou again
진희군은 왕저우에서 다시 퇴각했다.
I don't believe you are following me
당신이 나를 따라온다는 걸 믿을 수 없어요
no other plans
다른 계획은 없어
Then I'll keep chasing you
그럼 계속 쫓아갈게
Your Cui Jiajun
귀하의 Cui Jiajun
Will you give me half of the food?
음식을 절반만 주시겠어요?
What do you say?
당신은 무엇을 말합니까?
me
나
Never let others suffer
절대로 다른 사람이 고통받게 두지 마세요.
I want food
나는 음식을 원한다
But it has to be
하지만 그래야만 해
Get what you want in exchange
그 대가로 원하는 것을 얻으세요
Only then can I appear sincere and honest.
그래야만 성실하고 솔직해 보일 수 있어요.
Oh my god
맙소사
The emperor and his grandson are the whole world
황제와 그 손자는 온 세상이다.
most sincere
가장 진실한
The kindest person
가장 친절한 사람
My leg injury has healed
다리 부상이 나았네요
You don't need to take medicine anymore, right?
이제 더 이상 약을 먹을 필요가 없겠죠?
People like you are also afraid of taking medicine
너같은 사람도 약 먹는 걸 무서워해
Give me a drink quickly
빨리 한잔 줘
If you are in trouble
당신이 곤경에 처해 있다면
Turn back and meet the enemy
돌아서서 적을 만나다
What should I do if it drags me down?
그것이 나를 끌어내리면 어떻게 해야 합니까?
That's pretty much it
그 정도예요
reward for you
당신을 위한 보상
what
무엇
Candied fruit
설탕에 절인 과일
on the street today
오늘 거리에서
Looking at you, your eyes are burning
널 보면 눈이 불타오르고 있어
Stare at this thing
이것 좀 봐봐
I think you must like to eat
내 생각엔 네가 먹는 걸 좋아해야 할 것 같아
So I bought you a pack
그래서 내가 한 봉지 사줬어
Being courteous for nothing
괜히 예의바르고
what are you up to
지금 뭐하고 있어?
Since you have eaten my preserves
네가 내 보존 식품을 먹었으니
Do you want to come with me
나와 함께 가고 싶니?
Go and capture Bingzhou City
가서 빙저우성을 점령하라
A pack of preserves
보존 식품 팩
Just want me to take Bingzhou
그냥 내가 Bingzhou를 데려가길 바라
Emperor Sun, you have such a wishful thinking
태양 황제님, 당신은 그런 희망적인 생각을 갖고 계시군요
He played too well, right?
그 사람 너무 잘 놀았죠?
Han Li, Lord of Bingzhou City
빙저우 성주 한리(Han Li)
He's a cunning person
교활한 사람이네
A duplicitous villain
이중적인 악당
He refused earlier
그 사람이 아까 거절했는데
The court's order
법원의 명령
and the rebellious Sun Jing
그리고 반항적인 Sun Jing
Appearances are in harmony but detached from each other
겉모습은 조화롭지만 서로 떨어져 있다
All owned by Han Li
모두 한리 소유
However, merging the state and establishing the two cities
그러나 국가를 합병하고 두 도시를 설립하게 되면서
But these two places
그런데 이 두 곳은
At the crossroads of water and land
물과 땅의 교차점에서
Whether it's transporting food or using troops,
식량을 운반하는 일이든, 군대를 이용하는 일이든,
You have to go through these two places
이 두 곳을 거쳐야 해요
So the emperor's grandson
그래서 황제의 손자
Not only do they want to win Bingzhou
그들은 Bingzhou를 이기고 싶어할 뿐만 아니라
Together with Jianzhou
젠저우와 함께
I also want to take it together
나도 같이 갖고싶다
Distance from Jianzhou to Bingzhou
Jianzhou에서 Bingzhou까지의 거리
Just over two hundred miles
200마일이 조금 넘었어요
You can get there in one night
하룻밤이면 도착할 수 있어요
The general who defended the city of Jianzhou
건주(建州)성을 수호한 장군
Only recognize symbols but not people
기호만 인식하고 사람은 인식하지 못함
So as long as we
그러니 우리가 있는 한
Get Han Li's Tiger Talisman
한리의 호랑이 부적을 얻으세요
We will take Jianzhou
우리는 Jianzhou를 취할 것입니다
As long as we win Jianzhou
Jianzhou가 승리하는 한
Return with troops
군대와 함께 돌아오다
Nabingzhou
나빙저우
Nature is also in the bag
가방에도 자연이 담겨있습니다
and
그리고
I also found out a piece of news
저도 새로운 소식을 알아냈어요
Han Li has a new grandson
한리에게 새 손자가 생겼다
There will be a baby shower soon
곧 베이비 샤워가 있을 거예요
It seems
것 같다
We have to make a good backup gift
우리는 좋은 백업 선물을 만들어야 해
Send it to Han Li
한리에게 보내세요
Since it's a big gift
큰 선물이니까
Then you must prepare carefully
그럼 열심히 준비해야지
Only then can you please your master.
그래야만 주인을 기쁘게 할 수 있습니다.
This is the sincerity of Huangsun
이것이 바로 황순의 진심이다
The honest part
솔직한 부분
Want to use Bingzhou and Jianzhou
Bingzhou와 Jianzhou를 사용하고 싶습니다
Come in exchange for food from my Cui family army
우리 추이 가문 군대의 음식을 교환하러 오세요
It looks like you're injured
부상당한 것 같은데
It seems to be fine
괜찮은 것 같아요
Then I don't need it
그럼 필요없어
Couldn't be more sincere and honest
이보다 더 솔직하고 솔직할 수는 없다
starts tonight
오늘 밤부터 시작됩니다
You sleep on the floor
당신은 바닥에서 잔다
Ok, deal
좋아 그렇게하자
My injury hasn't healed yet
내 부상은 아직 낫지 않았어
Who said I was injured?
내가 다쳤다고 누가 그랬어요?
I can finally sleep in bed
드디어 침대에서 잘 수 있겠네요
There's not even a quilt on the ground
바닥에는 이불도 하나 없어
how can i sleep
어떻게 자면 돼?
I let you sleep
난 당신을 잠들게 했어요
The leg injury has obviously healed
다리 부상은 확실히 나았어
Don't let me take medicine
약을 먹지 못하게 해주세요
I drank medicine
나는 약을 마셨다
But let me sleep on the ground
하지만 땅바닥에서 자게 해주세요
What's the meaning
무슨 뜻인가요?
What's this
이게 뭐야?
open to take a look
열어서 구경해 보세요
How about it
어때요?
Looks good, right?
괜찮아 보이는데요?
It cost me a lot of money
돈이 많이 들었어
I ate your bag of preserves
나는 당신의 보존 식품 봉지를 먹었습니다
Let me help you plan to merge the states
주를 병합할 계획을 세우는 데 도움을 드리겠습니다.
I spent so much money today
오늘 돈을 너무 많이 썼다
You even bought some clothes for me.
나한테 옷도 사줬잖아.
It seems
것 같다
The plan is very big
계획은 매우 거창하다
Tomorrow happens to be the market day in Bingzhou
내일은 Bingzhou 장날입니다.
Let's go to the big market
큰 시장으로 가자
Not going
안 가요
You won't not go
당신은 가지 않을 것입니다
this was me yesterday
어제는 나였어
Clothes for you?
당신을 위한 옷?
How does it feel when you put it on?
바르면 어떤 느낌인가요?
Completely changed
완전히 바뀌었어요
How do you understand
어떻게 이해합니까?
Women's makeup
여성 메이크업
I'm specialized in
나는 전문적이다
Go to the clothing store
옷가게에 가세요
I changed into two pieces that fit better.
더 잘 어울리는 두 조각으로 바꿨어요.
And I bought you that silk flower
그리고 나는 당신에게 그 실크 꽃을 사줬어요
Replaced with a more beautiful one
더 예쁜걸로 교체했어요
Tongcaohua
통차오화
The lady is so beautifully dressed
아줌마 옷이 너무 이쁘네요
Husband today
오늘은 남편
I'm all a little bit frightened.
나는 모두 조금 겁이 난다.
Just put that thing on
그냥 그거 입으세요
No matter what happens, she will never look beautiful.
무슨 일이 있어도 그녀는 결코 아름다워 보이지 않을 것입니다.
How could that happen?
어떻게 그런 일이 일어날 수 있습니까?
Even in this world
이 세상에서도
All women dress like this
여자들은 다 이렇게 입는다
Then you are also the most beautiful one
그렇다면 역시 당신은 가장 아름다운 사람이에요
As expected, the emperor's grandson kept praising others
예상대로 황제의 손자는 계속 남을 칭찬했다.
They are all sincere and honest
다들 성실하고 정직해요
presumably
아마도
I need to use my place today
오늘은 내 자리를 이용해야 해요
Very much
흠뻑
That's natural
그건 당연해요
Lady’s hard work brings great rewards
레이디의 노력은 큰 보상을 가져옵니다
welcome
환영
I just asked
그냥 물어 봤어
Han Li's Mansion hired a new wet nurse
Han Li's Mansion은 새로운 유모를 고용했습니다.
I have a direct sister-in-law
직계동생이 있어요
Known as Lady Xu
쉬 부인(Lady Xu)으로 알려져 있음
Set up a stall during fairs
박람회 기간 동안 부스 설치
Selling soy milk and tofu
두유, 두부 판매
Cheerful and talkative
명랑하고 말이 많은
We'll play it by ear later
나중에 귀로 연주해 보겠습니다.
There's always a way to get her out of her words
그녀가 말을 하지 못하게 하는 방법은 항상 있어요
That being the case
그렇긴 한데
Go buy a piece of fine cloth
가서 좋은 천을 사오세요
Why buy fine cloth?
왜 좋은 옷을 사나요?
buy fine cloth
좋은 옷을 사다
Only then can I talk to Madam Xu.
그래야만 Xu 부인과 대화할 수 있습니다.
stupid
멍청한
Guest, your soy milk is here
손님 두유가 왔습니다
Please use it slowly
천천히 사용해 주세요
Thanks
감사해요
The soy milk cooked by my wife is so thick
아내가 끓인 두유가 너무 진해요
Really sweet
정말 달콤해요
That is
그건
Girls from all over the world
전 세계의 소녀들
Everyone loves my pot of soy milk
모두가 내 두유 한 그릇을 좋아해요
It tastes really good
맛이 정말 좋아요
little lady
작은 아가씨
This fine cloth
이 좋은 천
Are you buying this for your unborn baby?
아직 태어나지 않은 아기를 위해 이걸 사는 건가요?
yes
예
The young lady's home
젊은 아가씨의 집
Is there no mother or eldest sister?
엄마도 없고 큰 누나도 없나요?
How did the lady know?
그 여자는 어떻게 알았나요?
If there is a mother and eldest sister
엄마와 큰 누나가 있다면
Just know
그냥 알아
This new fine fabric
이 새로운 고급 원단
You can't make clothes for children
아이들을 위한 옷을 만들 수는 없어요
If you have old clothes, it would be best to have them remade
오래된 옷이 있다면 다시 만들어 입는 것이 가장 좋습니다.
Really not
정말 아니야
I can only use this fine cloth
이 좋은 천만 쓸 수 있어
washed and dried
씻어서 말렸다
Wash and dry again
다시 세탁하고 말리세요
Be sure to apply the paste on this new material
이 새로운 재료에 페이스트를 바르십시오.
It becomes soft after being washed
세탁하고 나면 부드러워지네요
Children’s skin is so tender
아이들 피부가 너무 부드러워요
If you use new cloth, it will definitely be worn out.
새 천을 사용하면 확실히 낡아지게 됩니다.
Thank you madam
감사합니다 부인
If my wife hadn’t reminded me
아내가 나에게 상기시키지 않았다면
I really don't know at all
나는 정말로 전혀 모른다.
Big mistake to make
저지르는 큰 실수
How can I thank you for this?
이것에 대해 어떻게 감사할 수 있습니까?
Just don't blame me for talking too much.
너무 말을 많이 한다고 해서 나를 비난하지 마세요.
The soy milk cooked by my wife is delicious
아내가 끓여준 두유가 맛있어요
People are enthusiastic
사람들은 열정적이다.
No wonder people nearby say
주변 사람들이 말하는 게 당연하지
Madam Xu is a very good person
Xu 부인은 매우 좋은 사람입니다.
How can I deserve such praise from you?
내가 어떻게 당신에게서 그런 칭찬을 받을 수 있겠습니까?
Lang Jun
랑준
I want to eat candied fruit
나는 설탕에 절인 과일을 먹고 싶다
Mr. Lang, go and buy some for me.
랭씨, 가서 좀 사주세요.
I'll rest here
난 여기서 쉴게요
There happen to be many things
일이 많이 생기네요
Want to be with Lady Xu
Lady Xu와 함께 있고 싶다
Ask for advice and advice
조언과 조언을 구하십시오
Good lady
좋은 아가씨
Walk slowly
천천히 걷기
Come on, come on, have another bowl
자, 자, 한 그릇 더 드세요
Lady
숙녀
Drink slowly
천천히 마시세요
Is the food here delicious?
여기 음식 맛있나요?
Yes, this is it
응, 바로 이거야
You are such a careful husband
당신은 정말 세심한 남편이에요
Will hurt people
사람들에게 상처를 줄 것이다
Store your soy milk money
두유 돈을 보관하세요
okay
좋아요
Come
오다
Lady Xu
레이디 쑤
Sit all morning
아침 내내 앉아있어
It's time for me to go back too
나도 이제 돌아갈 시간이야
Thank you for chatting with me so much
저와 많은 대화를 나눠주셔서 감사합니다
Business is light in the afternoon
오후에는 장사가 가벼워요
If you have time, come back another day
시간 있으면 다른 날 다시 오세요
I'll make bean curd for you to eat
내가 너희가 먹을 두부를 만들어 줄게
good
좋은
We will definitely come back
우리는 확실히 돌아올 것이다
Okay, walk slowly
알았어, 천천히 걸어
gone
다 쓴
How is your inquiry?
문의사항은 어떻습니까?
Of course, I need to find out clearly.
물론 명확하게 알아봐야 합니다.
The wet nurse of Han Mansion
한맨션의 유모
Biography
전기
Love and hate
사랑과 미움
Already know everything
이미 다 알고 있어
Can be useful
유용할 수 있음
This wet nurse
이 젖은 간호사
Like to eat Guanyin tofu
관음두부를 먹고 싶다
Love to eat millet
기장 먹는 걸 좋아해요
I also like to eat a kind of pickles
나도 피클 같은거 먹는 걸 좋아하는데
The locals call it Jin Buhuan
현지인들은 진 부환(Jin Buhuan)이라고 부릅니다.
What do you mean
무슨 뜻이에요
I know a little about pharmacology
나는 약리학에 대해 조금 알고 있습니다.
Eat these things together
이것저것 같이 먹어요
It doesn't matter, adults
상관없어요 어른들이여
But if the baby
하지만 아기라면
ate her milk
그녀의 우유를 먹었다
There will definitely be bloating and diarrhea
분명히 더부룩함과 설사가 있을 것입니다.
serious time
진지한 시간
Fever and rash
발열과 발진
I'm insinuating
나는 암시하고있다
I asked this lady
내가 이 아줌마한테 물어봤어
The wet nurse in Han Mansion
한맨션의 유모
My own two children
내 두 자녀
On the third and fourth day of the freshman year
1학년 셋째, 넷째 날
That's how I got sick
그래서 내가 아프게 됐어
so
그래서
Hanfu
한푸
I will definitely ask a doctor
꼭 의사한테 물어볼게요
give you
당신에게